Guide to the WSU Press Records 1948-1992
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
WSU Press Records
1948-1992
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives and Special Collections
Archives 403
Washington State University. Press
2.25 Linear feet of shelf space 5 Boxes
Records of the WSU (Washington State University) Press from 1948 to 1992. The collection contains administrative records, correspondence, and publishing proposals and evaluations.
Originally created in the late 1920s by Washington State University (WSU) President Ernest O. Holland, the WSU Press began as a committee focused on scholarly publishing. In April 1929, the Press distributed its first scholarly journal, Research Studies. This journal became WSU’s primary academic publishing outlet until the mid-1940s. Another scholarly journal was added to WSU Press in 1947, Northwest Science, which originated with the Northwest Scientific Association and had already been established for 20 years prior. Northwest Science is still an active journal with the Press as of 2022.
An influential figure in the history of the Press was University Editor Henry Grosshans, who made sweeping changes starting in the 1950s and remained a dynamic force in the Press until his retirement in 1982. Grosshans helped establish journals such as Poe Studies and ESQ: A Journal of the American Renaissance. He also published the works of authors such as Robert Nilan, Arthur Stabler, and John Cutts.
The Press collaborated with the WSU Museum of Art to publish exhibit catalogs including "Gaylen Hansen: The Paintings of a Decade, 1975-1985". In 1990, WSU Press published the three-volume Centennial Histories as part of WSU’s 100th anniversary celebration. The three books include "Going to Washington State: A Century of Student Life" by William Stimson, "The Crimson and the Gray: 100 Years with the WSU Cougars" by Richard Fry, and "Creating the People’s University: Washington State University, 1890-1990" by George Frykman.
The WSU Press records consist of administrative records such as budgets and minutes, correspondence between the Press and authors, publishing proposals and evaluations from reviewers, and chapter drafts and reviewer edits for George Frykman’s Washington State University Centennial Histories book "Creating the People’s University". These records span from 1948 to 1992. This collection also includes two undated music printing plates of Washington, My Washington and The Fight Song.
This collection is arranged in four series. The first three subject-based series are arranged alphabetically, with folders arranged alphabetically by subject within that series. The fourth series consists of the two music printing plates.
This collection is open and available for research use.
WSU Press Editor-in-Chief Fred Bohm donated most of this collection to the Washington State University Libraries’ Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections in November 1990. These records spanned from 1948 to 1990 and were retained as UA1990-33. Leslie Little of WSU Press donated one envelope of correspondence dating from 1985 to 1992. Half of that envelope was retained and the rest was returned; the remainder was retained as UA2013-08.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Washington State University. Press -- Records and correspondence
Publishers and publishing -- Washington (State) -- Records and correspondence
Publishers and publishing; Washington (State)
- Series 1: Administration, 1962-1992
  - Book sales and accounts, 1985-1990 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Financial support, budgets, and statements for journals. I, 1982-1987 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Financial support, budgets, and statements for journals. II, 1982-1987 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Hand Associates publishing contract and correspondence, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Meeting minutes, 1987-1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Meeting minutes, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Photographs and negatives of publishing events and authors, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Publication checklists and pagination outlines, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Status reports and goals, 1986-1990 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Series 2: Correspondence, 1960-1992
  - Administration, 1969-1989 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Administration, 1990-1992 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Association for Tropical Biology, 1970-1983 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Barley Genetics II. Nilan, Robert, 1962-1984 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Book proposals, 1983-1988 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Chinese-English Translation Assistance Group (CETA), 1980-1984 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Genus Tilletia. Duran, Ruben. Fischer, George, 1960-1965 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - International Conference on Projective Planes, 1973-1984 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Journals, 1982-1988 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Latin America, 1968-1976 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Lowenfels, Walter, 1969-1984 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - McCord, Howard, 1965-1970 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - McElroy, Davis Dunbar, 1969-1984 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Permissions for publication and reprinting, 1965-1974 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Picard, Raymond, 1968-1984 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Rich and Strange. Cutts, John, 1968-1982 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Sheldon, Charles, 1978-1984 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Stabler, Arthur, 1971-1988 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Thompson, Richard, 1973-1987 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Valko, Laszlo, 1964-1968 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Walker, Deward, 1966-1982 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Washington Centennial Commission, 1985-1989 (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Series 3: Publications, 1948-1990
  - Creating the People's University. Frykman, George. Chapter drafts and edits. I, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Creating the People's University. Frykman, George. Chapter drafts and edits. II, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Creating the People's University. Frykman, George. Chapter drafts and edits. III, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Creating the People's University. Frykman, George. Chapter drafts and edits. IV, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Daugherty project, 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Gaylen Hansen biographical details and brochure, 1981-1985 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Journal brochures and general information, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Julia Stephen stories publication correspondence, 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Kaiser's agricultural history of the Palouse, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Northwest Science journal budget and correspondence, 1948-1982 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Palouse Country: An Essay in Photographs. Bedirian, George. Correspondence and critique, 1983-1986 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Pictorial history of Washington State. Proposals and outlines, 1987-1989 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Publishing proposals and evaluations, 1985-1990 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Start the Presses. Cloud, Barbara. Correspondence and draft, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 45)
- Series 4: Music Printing Plates
  - The Fight Song, Undated (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Washington, My Washington, Undated (Box 5, Folder 47)